Inventory of Central Pacific Railroad Documents Collection MS 79 MS 79
Test
Central Pacific Railroad Collection
1861-1959
Test
MS 79
388.5 Linear Feet 377 Boxes + 19 volumes
The Central Pacific Railroad Collection contains eights series filled with records from various departments within the Central Pacific from the mid nineteenth to the early twentieth century. The collection contains series on personnel, financial records, and documents from the Shop, Land, and Office of the Secretary, as well as tarriff waybills.
Conditions Governing Access
Some Restrictions apply. Contact Library Staff for details
Scope and Contents
¶ The Central Pacific Collection contains eight series of documents and files from various sectors of the Central Pacific Railroad Company. The earliest documents in this collection are dated 1861, while the latest go to 1959. Thus this collection represents nearly one-hundred years of railroad history. ¶
¶ The largest series in this collection are the financial records which span the length of the entire series (1861-1959). Notable financial records include the purchase of locomotives, rolling stock, equiptment, and building materials by C. P. Huntington for the company, as well as handwritten entries into the Huntington Cash Book giving intricate details of the purchases arranged in chronological order. There are two additional cash books that likewise contain handwritten entries, as well as newspaper and political clippings pertaining to events in Sacramento circa 1870. Finally, there is a collection of invoices, notes, and bills from vendors to the Central Pacific company from the 1860s and 1880s. ¶
¶ The next four series contain various documents and forms from the Land, Engineering, Equiptment, and Personnel sections of the Central Pacific. The Engineering series contains vouchers, invoices, inventory, and payroll ledgers for the department that detail what was purchased between 1862 and 1863, the list of employees and what they made during that same period, and an inventory of the shops in 1861 and 1873. The Personnel series consists entirely of payroll sheets from the Central Pacific Contruction Department (responsible for the actual building of the railroad), and includes handwritten details from Charles Crocker about the workers, their position, rate of pay, and total pay These records span from 1864 to 1866. Included in the writings are details on the Chinese gangs that worked seperately from the rest of the general labor force, and a single volume on unpaid wages from 1882-1885. The Eqiptment secion contains several boxes of specificaltions and schematics of various cars built and used by the Central Pacific between 1868 and 1929. Included are the schematics for passenger cars (1st class and coach), freight cars, and pieces of equiptment used to maintain them. ¶
¶ The Land Depatment series contains eight volumes of property books that detail all of the lands owned by the Central Pacific in Oregon, California, Nevada, and Utah between 1910 and 1949. There is additionally a three volume set of day books containing records of deeds, contracts, and cancellations from 1870 to 1883. Finally there is one volume containing station schematics from circa 1880. ¶
¶ The final three sections concern tariff forms, miscellaneous documents, and letters from the Office of the Secretary. The Tariff section contains samples of tariff forms for passenger and freight cars from the Central Pacific, as well as the Union Pacific railroad companies from 1875 to 1878. The miscellaneous series contains a litany of forms, including lists of tools on each locomotive, meteorlogical observation charts, and wage forms for personnel. The dates of the misc. section vary from the 1870s, through the early 1900s. The section concerning the Offic of the Secretary contains fifteen volumes that deal with bond records, mortgage rates, and coupons from 1899 to 1917. ¶
Central Pacific Railroad Company; Railroads--California--History
- Series 1: Financial Records, 1861-1959
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restrictions in place. Contact Library Staff for details
  Scope and Contents
  ¶ Early Central Pacific Railroad financial transactions were not divided by department. This Series includes company-wide transactions.¶
  ¶ Notable financial records cover purchases made for the company in New York by Collis P. Huntington for a period of over twenty years. Purchases include locomotives (including Central Pacific Railroad locomotive No. 1, "Gov. Stanford," and locomotive No. 3, "C. P. Huntington"), rolling stock, equipment components, construction equipment and supplies, and general stores. Handwritten entries in the C.P. Huntington cash books are arranged by month and contain the date purchased, name of the supplier, description of the material purchased, cost, shipping charges, and names and sailing dates of the vessels on which the merchandise was shipped to California. In later volumes transportation by rail is indicated. ¶
  ¶Two other early cash books, 1861-1870 and 1863-1869 also have extensive handwritten notes as well as newspaper clippings from Sacramento and other newspapers of the time affixed to the inside of the boards and to the end papers. In addition 1861-1870 has political handbills affixed to the end papers. ¶
  ¶ The Central Pacific Railroad vouchers comprise a key element in the California State Railroad Museum's Southern Pacific Railroad Company Records. They are among the earliest items in the collection. Some date prior to the incorporation of the Central Pacific. The early vouchers contain such information as payrolls for teams surveying the route across the Sierra Nevada, purchases of equipment for the surveys, and purchases of newspaper advertisements for the incorporation of the Central Pacific and for the initiation of construction. Later vouchers cover such items as the acquisition of equipment and supplies for building the railroad as well as for its early operation. Prominent individuals mentioned in the voucher collection include Theodore D. Judah, Leland Stanford, Charles Crocker, Mark Hopkins, Collis P. Huntington, and Alfred Hart. ¶
  ¶ The vouchers are arranged by year and then by voucher number (which results in rough chronological order). Each number series in parentheses equals one document box. ¶
  ¶ Notes and bills payable and receivable, 1863-1866 is a record book of notes and bills due to and payable by the Central Pacific Railroad for the period May 2, 1863 to September 1, 1866. Information may include date, drawer, payee, on what account, time, when due, amount and if paid. Includes records of short term notes drawn by the Central Pacific, Leland Stanford, and Collis P. Huntington. Also records interest payments by CP on bonds issued by the State of California. Sacramento County, and Placer County. ¶
  ¶ Invoices, September 1882- November 1883 contains invoices from vendors with corresponding Central Pacific expense bills, have been pasted into a scrapbook in roughly chronological order. There is a subject index at the beginning of the volume. Purchases cover a wide variety of products including materials for the construction of locomotives and rolling stock, fittings, waste, oil, lumber, glass, lanterns and drafting supplies as well as employee badges and tools. Selected companies include Westinghouse Air Brake, National Car Spring Company, Ensign Manufacturing Company, National Car Spring Company, John A. Roebling, Chicago Car Seal, and M. J. Goodenough, manufacturer of ostrich feather dusters. ¶
  Central Pacific Railroad Company; Railroads--California--History
- Series 2: Engineering Department Records, 1861-1873; 2.5 Linear Feet 2 Boxes. 1 Volume
  Restrictions in place. Contact Library Staff for details.
  ¶ This series contains invoice, payroll, and inventory papers from the Central Pacific Engineering Department seperated into two boxes and one volume binder. The invoice box contains information such as vendor name, date of invoice, description and amount of payment organized chronologically from 1861 to 1863. ¶
  ¶ Monthly payroll information, including employee name, occupation, dates of employment, rate of pay, monies owed, and signature of employee indicating receipt of pay. Job classifications include engineer, leveler, flagman, transit man, rodman, chainman, teamster, axeman, draughtsman, office assistant and copyist. Many of the payrolls bear the signatures of noted figures: Theodore Dehone Judah (1826-1863), George Henry Goddard (1817-1906), (government surveyor and artist) and Samuel Skerry Montague. ¶
  ¶ Finally, the inventory selection includes a descriptive inventory of physical characteristics at principal facilities. Completeness of information under each category varies, but may include elevation, date laid out, distance from end point, engineering station numbers, dimensions of structures, costs, construction dates. A Southern Pacific R[esearch] T[eam]. The inventoried sites include the Central Pacific Yard at Ogden, UT, the Oregon Branch, and various facilities in Northern and Central California. Inventories sheets are dates between 1861 and 1873. ¶
  - Subseries 1: Invoices and Vouchers
  - Subseries 2: Payroll
  - Subseries 3: Inventory
- Series 3: Land Department Records, 1870-1949; 12 Volumes
  Restictions in place. Contact Library Staff for details.
  ¶ This series consists of twelve volumes of records and documents pertaining to the Land Department of the Central Pacific Railroad. The bulk of the series are the eight property map books ultilized by Central Pacific and Southern Pacific from 1910 to 1949. The books contain land grant information for properties in California, Nevada, and Utah which were owned by the railraods. Legal descriptions of the properties are given on each page of maps, with each section of land depicted divided into sixteenths. The volumes cover both Central Pacific and Southern Pacific Railroads, with four volumes for each. ¶
  ¶ The next largest group are the three volumes of day books used by Central Pacific to record the sale of lands in California from 1870 to 1883. They are arranged chronologically, and include entries for land purchase contracts, cancellations and deeds. Each entry notes the date of the transaction, contract numbers, the person(s) to whom the property was sold, terms of the sale, location of the property and amount received. Also included are right of way, mineral, or other reservations. ¶
  ¶ Finally, there is a single volume containing hand drawn station plans from circa. 1880. The plans were used by Central Pacific to build stations for their Salt Lake, Humboldt, and Truckee divisions in California, Nevada, and Utah. ¶
  Central Pacific Railway Company; Railroads--California--History
- Series 4: Personnel Records, 1864-1885; 7 Linear Feet 7 Boxes.
  ¶ This series consists of construction payroll sheets for the building of the Central Pacific Railroad. The payrolls are handwritten on printed forms and were issued by the railroad for "C[harles] Crocker, Contractor." The payrolls list the construction division for which the individual worked, rates of pay, and total pay received. The collection includes some payroll sheets for Chinese labor gangs, as well as payroll information for James Strobridge and other construction officials. ¶
  ¶ The payrolls are numbered consecutively for the period 1864-1865. A new consecutive numbering system seems to have been instituted in 1866, starting again with the number one. The payrolls are arranged by year and then by number. The CSRM Library does not have a complete set; there are missing numbers within each year. An inventory to the payroll vouchers, prepared when they were in the possession of Southern Pacific, has been placed in each box. While the inventory is not complete, it does identify specific Camps, Camp officials, as well as the vouchers which record Chinese labor. Refer to other MS 79 series for additional personnel information. View a sample payroll (No. 102 dated March 1865) online at: www.sachistoryonline.org.¶
  ¶ There is also a single volume relating to unpaid wages, 1882-1885. ¶
- Series 5: Equipment Records, 1868-1929; 3 Linear Feet 2 volumes and 2 boxes
  ¶ This series consists of two volumes and two boxes that contain an inventory of the equiptment and train cars used by the Central Pacific from the late ninteenth, to the early twentieth century. ¶
  ¶ The first volume provides the names of floating equipment or the numbers (old and new) of locomotives or cars, class of equipment, dimensions, weight, date in service and remarks, including disposition of the equipment. The cars listed in this volume are mainly an assortment of passenger cars (observation, sleeper, coach, etc), as well as shop and work cars used for construction and snow clearing projects. ¶
  ¶ The scecond volume contains similar information, but deals more with the weight capacity of box and freight cars. The volume also specifically lists fruit cars, cotton hoppers, and flat freight cars. Like the other volume, this one is dated between 1899 and 1929. ¶
  ¶ The two boxes contain mimeographed forms (Form 116: [form number was from original box; the forms have no numbers] with ink entries. In tabular form the following information may have been entered: owner, class, car number, date placed in service, capacity, original cost (actual / estimated), depreciation (percentage per year / amount per month), date vacated. One box has details the various car types used by specific branches of the Central Pacific Railroad. The two boxes are divided alphabetically, and cover the period between 1868 and 1808. ¶
  - Record Equipment Books
  - Rolling Stock
- Series 6: Miscellaneous Documents, Forms, and Correspondence, 1869-1903; 2 Linear Feet 2 Boxes
  ¶ Included in this collection are miscellaneous forms issued by the Central Pacific Railroad. By studying the types of information recorded, it is possible to learn details about the operation of the railroad and its personnel. This sampling represents but a minuscule portion of those issued or received by the Central Pacific. The forms have been arranged into two sub-series (blank and completed) and then by number or issuing department. The contents of these various documents range from waybill recipts and machinery department reports, to land department forms and livestock freight recipts. The forms range in date from 1869 to 1903 ¶
  Railroads--California--History; Central Pacific Railroad Company
- Series 7: Tariffs, 1875-1882; 5 Linear Feet 5 Boxes
  ¶ This series includes sample freight and passenger tariffs for the Central Pacific Railroad. There are also some joint tariffs, with the Union Pacific Railroad. Freight tariffs may list commodities, rates based on distance, and various shipping regulations. Tariffs come in various formats and are difficult to interpret unless one has all the appropriate issues and tables. Unfortunately, when a new tariff was issued, the previous edition was usually discarded, thus making it difficult for contemporary collectors to compile complete sets. ¶
- Series 8: Office of the Secretary, 1899-1917; 15 Volumes
  ¶ This series contains 15 volumes of bond ledger, recipt, and transfer books from the Central Pacific Railroad Company's Office of the Secretary between 1899 and 1917. The volumes are divided into three section. The first is three volumes mainly focusing on registered mortgage and gold rates from 1900 to 1914. The second are recipt books that cover a similar topic of gold and mortgage from 1900 to 1917. The final section deals with bond transfer books from 1905 to 1917. ¶
  - Bond Ledgers
  - Bond Receipt Books
  - Bond Transfers